黑客们好，欢迎回到PWN学院
hello hackers welcome back to pwn college
今天我们要讨论的是
today we're talking about
漏洞利用场景
exploitation scenarios
这个模块
this is a module
把我们以前学到的结合到一起
that puts together everything we've Learned in previous modules
并加以应用
and applies it
这个视频主要讨论利用内存错误
this specifically is a discussion about the use of memory error
在程序中注入shellcode并运行
to inject shellcode and run shellcode into in a program
我们在shellcode模块中讲过很多它的使用方法和场景
we've run shellcode and all sorts of different scenarios in module 2
在内存错误模块
and in module 5
我们讲了很多内存错误及其利用
we did a whole lot of memory error exploitations of the impacts of memory errors
现在要把它们结合到一起
now we're going to put them together
回想一下,
recall that
内存错误和控制劫持是同时发生的
memory errors and controlful hijack occurs in part
因为控制信息和数据是混合的
because of the mixing of control and information data
起初程序有代码在text段
right so when you have a program starting off that has code in the text segment section
有数据、堆和栈，有用户控制的
data and the heap and the stack and there is user controlled
或者当用户是攻击者时，攻击者控制的
or what is attacker controlled when the user is an attacker
在栈上和控制信息，例如返回地址，放在一起的数据
data that is on the stack interlieved with control information such as return addresses
正如您在前面的模块中看到的那样
as you've seen in the previous module
事情可能会变得危险
things can get dicey
我们将在这里探讨可能变得危险的方式之一
one of the ways that they can get dicey that we're going to explore here
是当返回地址被覆盖，并且
is when a return address is over written and
通过覆盖返回地址程序被重定向到shellcode中
by being overwritten  it ends up redirecting control flow into shellcode all right
示例使用shellcoding模块中的示例
for our example we're going to recall the example from the shellcodeing module
就是这个
this was it
这是一个简单的程序，有一个非常愚蠢的错误
it's a simple program with a really dumb bug
实际上是2个bug
actually 2 bugs
但是在shellcoding上下文中
but in the shellcodeing context
这个bug是hello调用的参数混淆了
the bug was that the argument to this call of hello were mixed up
该传函数指针，结果传了name变量
instead of the function pointer for bye func the name was passed in
我们可以直接把name当作shellcode执行
and so we could directly execute the name as shellcode
这些bug的发生令人震惊
these bugs happen shockingly
但这种情况很少发生
but they happen fairly rarely
这需要忽略大量编译器警告
this takes a lot of ignoring of compiler warnings to occur
这个程序还有一个bug
this program has another bug
即使你修复了
and even if you fix the bug
这个在shellcoding模块中讲的允许任意代码执行的bug
that allowed for arbitrary execution of shellcode in the shellcodeing module
我们还有个问题
we still have a problem
这个问题是gets函数
and that problem is gets
Gets在任何情况都是一个不安全的函数
gets is a function that is always unsafe
在这种情况下，当然也是的
and in this case yeah
这是典型的老式缓冲区溢出
it's a typical classic old school buffer overflow
典型到如果使用gets，编译器都会向你报警
to the point where the compiler will complain at you if you use gets
但很明显，正如你在之前的模块中看到的
but obviously as you've seen in the previous module
这些错误会非常频繁地在不同的场景中发生
these errors can occur quite frequently in a lot of varied scenarios where
即使开发人员实际上非常注意大小
even when developers are actually careful about sizing
在这种情况下，我们有一个栈缓冲区溢出
so in this case we have a stack buffer overflow
当然，你们现在对这个已经很熟悉了
and of course as you are well familiar by now
可以覆盖返回地址
you can overwrite the return address and
重定向到你想要的地方
redirect to you should know wherever you want
当然，这个程序没有win 函数
of course this program doesn't have a win function
没有能让你直接读到flag的函数
there's no function that allows you to hijack to read the flag
你必须自己写一个
you have to write it yourself
这就是shellcode注入
and of course that is shellcode injection
好吧
all right
让我们来看一看
let's take a look
提醒一下
as a reminder
这是一个非常简单的例子，我们禁用了很多保护措施
this is a very simple example we have a lot of mitigations disabled with
有意思，等一下
that's interesting hold on
让我修正一下这里的文本设置
let me fix my text setup here
好吧
all right
让我们先看一下
let's 1st take a look
我首先在这里写了这个程序。hello.c
I first wrote this program out here. hello.c
和幻灯片上的一样，并且修复了这个传错参数的bug
we have the exact thing from the slides with the bug fixed
如果你运行这个
right so if you run this
我们来编译一下
um let's compile it
正如我提到的
as I mentioned
我要关闭一堆保护机制
I'm turning off a bunch of mitigation
我允许了可执行栈
I'm turning on an executable stack
我们要注入shellcode到那里
that's where we're going to inject our shellcode
我关掉了栈金丝雀
and I'm turning off um stack canaries
您已经从前面的模块中了解了这些含义
you understand what those implications are from the previous modules
但我们要先从一个简单的例子开始
but we're gonna start with a very simple example here
之后再讨论如何处理更复杂的示例
talk about how to tackle more complex examples later
我们会
and we will
之后你们会在练习题中探索很多
and then you will explore a lot of that on your own at the practice problems
好了，编译它
all right so we compile this and
正如我提到的，如果使用gets，编译器会报警
as I mentioned if you use gets the compiler complaints at you right
当然，这些bug还会以其他方式出现
of course there are other ways that these bugs gonna occur
好，我们来执行它
all right let's execute it
输入名字
we put it on our name
然后它会回你好
and then it just says hello
然后随机选一个bye函数执行
and then tells us one of 2 randomly chosen goodbye functions
好的，太棒了
alright awesome so
这就是我们要利用的程序
so this is the program of how do we exploit it
很明显
obviously
如果我们输入大量的文本
if we put in a whole lot of text
它会崩溃
it'll crash
让我们来看看为什么
let's take a look at why
它将在从主函数返回时崩溃
it'll crash at the ret from the main function
如果我们看一下栈，它被A的OX41覆盖了
and if we look at the stack it was over written by A's OX41
这就是为什么它会崩溃
and that's why it's crashing all right
如果你看一下进程内存映射
if you look at the process map
你可以看到我们的栈是可执行的
you can see that our stack is executable um
这个进程，让我们快速看一下
here's the process let's just take a quick look
好了，这样就能看权限了
okay here it is with the permissions
你可以看到我们的栈是可执行的
you can see our stack is executable
因为之前用execstack编译的
because you compiled with execstack and
如你所见，没有触发金丝雀
as you saw there was no canary triggered
程序返回到我们覆盖的返回地址时，没被终止
to kill the program  before it could return to our overwritten return address
很酷
cool
现在我们只需要构建漏洞利用程序
so now we just need to build the exploit
我们要做的是
what we're going to do is
我们会用（想要的）返回地址溢出缓冲区
we're going to overflow the buffer with our return address ummm
溢出缓冲区，修改返回地址
with overflow the buffer modify the return address
指向我们写入了代码的缓冲区
to point into the buffer that we're writing
也就是我们放shellcode的位置
where we'll put shellcode
因为栈是可执行的
since that's executable
shellcode将被执行，我们可以开始了
the shellcode will execute and we'll be good to go
我们要用pwntools来做这个
we're gonna do this with pwntools
特别是使用PWN调试功能
specifically using the pwn debug functionality
pwntools很好，它允许我们禁用ASLR
and pwntools is nice that allows us to disable ASLR
我们在这个基本演示中禁用了所有的保护措施
so we're disabling really all mitigations for this basic demo
这样我们可以直接覆盖写入正确的地址
so that we can of course set the right address
这样我们就知道发送什么地址了
so that we know what address to send
我们启动PWN，程序正在运行
so we we start up pwn here is is the program running
你要做的第一件事就是弄清楚
the 1st thing you got to do is figure out
返回地址离缓冲区有多远
how far away the return address is from the buffer
我们使用一个循环模式
we're going to be super lazy and use a cyclic pattern
我们写pwn.cyclic
so we're going to write pwn.cyclic
当然是64位的机器
of course it's a 64 bit machine
我们写2000字节，每8字节为一个单位
so let's just write 2 000 bytes with 8 bytes at a time
这样我们就可以按8字节查找
so that we can look up with with 8 bytes
并且gets是不安全
and gets is unsafed
因为它总是读到换行符
because it always reads to the new line
它根本不关心它读取的字节数
it has no no it doesn't care at all about the amount of bytes its read
gets肯定会导致缓冲区溢出
gets is almost guaranteed buffer overflow again
但是我们需要换行符，这样它才能停止
but we need a new line so that it stops reading
好的，我们这样写了。boom
all right we wrote that. boom
段错误
segmentation fault
让我们看看栈上返回地址被什么覆盖了
let's see what is the stack got overwritten with
栈被这些无意义的内容覆盖了
the stack got overwritten with this nonsense
这是我们循环模式的一部分
this is part of our cyclic pattern
说一下
for the record
如果我们打印生成的循环模式
if we generate this pattern
这就是我们的循环模式
this is the cyclic pattern we overflowed with
当然
and of course
这是
this is
如果我们看一下RSP中的字符串
if we look at RSP in a string
你可以看到这是循环模式的一部分
you can see this is part of it right
这是它的小端序
and so that this is this in a little endian
我们可以查询其中任何一个在循环模式中的位置
and we can query either one of those
你可以执行pwn.find
you can do pwn.find
cyclic_find
被覆盖后的返回地址和
that address and
=8。这是循环模式的步长
equals 8 that's the step size of the cyclic pattern
它的位置是1032
and it's at position 10 32
所以我们要发送1032个填充字符
so we have to send 10 32 of anything
然后我们覆盖返回地址，然后
and then we overflow with the return address and then
我们可以把shellcode放在后面
we can put shellcode after that
或者我们可以把shellcode放在前面
or we could put shellcode before that
但放在后面，运行时计算偏移量会更容易一些
but after it's a little easier to calculate offsets on the fly
我们把它放后面
so we're gonna do that here
好了，最后一件事是
all right the final thing is
当返回发生时，栈指向这里
the stack is pointing here when the return occurs
所以我们要做的是
so what we're going to do is
用 这个+8，shellcode所在的位置，来覆盖返回地址
overwrite the return address with 8B past this location  where our shellcode will be
我们来看一下
so let's let's take a look at that
我们要重新启动
we're going to relaunch
首先
1st of all
好吧
okay
在这里继续
continue here
好了，我们到了
alright so here we are
写1032个a
we're going to write 1032 As
然后我们
and then we're going to pack
用p64处理这个加8
P 64 of course takes this plus 8
p64将这个数转换为一个小端序的字符串
takes this number and converse it to a little endian string
加上我们的shellcode
plus our shellcode
这将用一个指向返回地址后8个字节的指针覆盖返回地址
right so this will overwrite the return address with a pointer to 8 bytes after the return address
我们把shellcodes放在那里
which is where we'll put our shellcodes
当main返回时
so when main returns
我们的shellcode将运行
boom our shellcode will run
现在我们放入shellcode
and now we put in the shellcode
我已经写在这里了
I actually already wrote it here
这只是一个简单的打开，发送文件的shellcode
this is just a simple open sent file shellcode
这是结果，当我运行它时，它读取我的假旗帜
here's the results it reads my fake flag when I run it
就在这里
and it's right here
我们复制一下
let's just copy this
哦
oops
粘贴
paste it
还有我们的换行符
and our new line
好吧
okay
我们这样写
we write this
这里我们看到它在非法指令下崩溃了
here we see it crashed on illegal instruction
这很有可能是在shellcode执行完之后崩溃的
that's promising probably right after our shellcode
嗯，让我看看
um and let's see
我们将返回结果都读出来会看到什么
what happened if we read everything
终止
terminated okay
我们开始吧
here we go it
shellcode运行并读取了我们的flag
the shellcode ran and it read our flag
我们在这里做了什么
so what did we do here
我们溢出了name的缓冲区
we overflowed the name buffer
当gets运行时，它溢出覆盖了main的返回地址
when gets ran it overflow the return address of main
当main返回时，它返回到栈中
when main returned it returned onto the stack
因为我们编译它的方式，导致栈是可执行的
which was executable because of the way we compiled it
现代程序则不是这样
modern programs this is not the case
所以我们可以运行shellcode
and we were able to run our shellcode and
读取flag
read the flag
结合了内存损坏和shellcode执行
combination of memory corruption and shellcode execution
太棒了，接下来的课程我们会
awesome through the rest of the module we'll
看看其他的不同组合
look at a couple of other concepts around these various combinations
然后你们会在练习单元的练习题中进行练习
and then you will practice them in the practice modules in the practice problems
祝你好运
good luck